[Music]
so
hello welcome
it is september 14 2022 and we're in
active livestream number 48.2
welcome to the active inference
institute
we're participatory online institute
that is communicating learning and
practicing applied active inference you
can find us at some of the links on the
slide
this is a recorded and an archived live
stream so please provide feedback so we
can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome here and we'll follow a video
etiquette for live streams
head over to activeinference.org to
learn more about
how to participate in learning groups
and projects such as live streams and
others
well we are in
our third discussion around this paper
communication as socially extended
active inference and ecological approach
to communicative behavior from 2021
by remy tison and pierre poirier and
last week in 48.1
with
the very same
fellows in the conversation
we had some explorations into
different aspects of the paper
perhaps we can each say
hello again
and something if we want to that we
remembered from last week or that we'd
like to
explore today and then we can just be
right in it
so
i'm daniel i'm in california
and i'm interested to
look towards the latter half the back
nine
of the paper
and see where we go which is kind of
what we do in dot twos
usually
and i just have a feeling that
the exit from the slide on this one
may put our
communication and situatedness in a
different place
than where we were before
and i'll pass it to blue
hi i'm blue i'm a
i heard the initial part and then lost
it blue
yep can you hear me now how about that
um i am uh blue and i'm a researcher in
new mexico and i am excited to dig back
into
this paper i think we left a lot of
things to wonder about last week and um
and yeah excited to get to maybe more
into the meat of the paper itself as
opposed to just
discussing tangential ideas
um and i'll pass today
blue i'm dean i'm here in calgary um
i'm interested in seeing whether or not
the big road map that i think that this
paper provides
also ex could be explained as a big
score as as in a kind of a musical
analogy because i'm really interested in
the
in the interplay or the interaction
between orchestration and arrangements
we
yesterday there was a math stream
that
where our guest was um
really good at sort of
describing the arrangement part of of
what's going on in active inference
potentially and so i'm really kind of
interested in looking at that because
i think from a transmission versus
ecological standpoint we're kind of
looking at the difference between mono
and stereo
so i'm wondering if we should maybe
look at that through that lens as well
i'll pass it to remy
hi i'm uh i'm a researcher at ucam
in montreal and i'm the author of the of
the paper
and i'm looking forward to discussing
the yes the the paper more in detail and
maybe go to uh
toward the the later parts of the paper
and maybe talk about a bit about uh
language and linguistic communication
which is a a big piece that is looming
behind the paper but it's not really
that much discussed in it but i think
that's what
that's what any account of communication
aims to
go towards so
i hope we'll have the chance to discuss
it a little bit
let's go
to language
it's what we're using among other
modalities but we are using language
and
so that sounds like a great place to
start so what was in the paper regarding
language
and what was not in the paper regarding
uh yeah so um
the the idea was to open a window uh
at the end of the paper towards the
language so we talked a bit about uh
conventional
uh forms of communication and we know
that most people
believe that language is conventional so
we tried to tie
our
the ideas that we put forward
in the paper with a work by hampstead uh
in a paper of 2016 about conventional
affordances so we tried to say that uh
um
that linguistic communicate the
conventional nature of the language
comes from the the conventional
affordances that are generated in the
in in the
communicative interaction so that's what
that's a way to point toward language in
our
account
and
we talked a bit about uh
acts of different types of acts of
language so
informative or uh
or declarative and uh interrogative
imperative so these kinds of
distinctions we try to account for them
in our framework so there are
these are various
parts of what we consider to be language
that we try to treat in the paper but
there's a lot of things that we
couldn't discuss
obviously because it was like in the in
the
small section and at the end we cannot
like explain all of language
even in a paper or in a book
so so in a small section that would be
obviously way too ambitious
what are we looking to explain or what
is needed for language to be
encompassed or at home or native to the
ecological view
rather than the transmission view or in
addition to the transmission view
redmi first then others yeah a point
that is interesting is that
um
the transmission view comes with a a
presupposition presuppressor position
about what has to be explained by a
theory of
of language it comes with the idea that
we have to account for the meaning
uh
of the the the expressions that are used
first so we have to understand what are
the meanings of the words that we use
and how these meanings are encoded in
the in the brains and the heads of the
the the
of the speakers of the language
but that that's
uh
misleading from the point of view that
we adapt in the paper so
this
it's kind of hard to say uh what we have
to explain in order to explain language
because for so long uh
we have based in the we have
been in the the the
the transmission view and so we are used
to uh believe that in order to explain
language we have to explain these kinds
of
contents that language transmits uh so
but if we do away with these contents
it's kind of uh
open the question of how do we account
for language it becomes kind of open in
a new way
and i i don't really know exactly what
we have to account
for
in order to account for language because
it kind of changes uh our view of what
language is so i i think there's a lot
of open space uh in
in
this question of how do we account for
language if we do away with the
transmission view
d or blue
what do you got blue
so i just was looking back over the
paper i think um it might be useful to
maybe delineate the the specific like
types of language interrogative versus
imperative um
and like the specif the specificities
underlying each one of those right now
um that would be maybe a good place to
to just dive into the meat of the paper
how can we see these different types of
speech
speech acts
as shaping the field of affordances
what is being done ecologically
with these different speech
behaviors
as opposed to the
enabling
aspect of the transmission view i think
they're fairly clear within the
transmission view
what these
uh statements are about and as you
pointed out it's almost like hard to
escape viewing
what these speech behaviors are
by the content like if not their content
quite literally then what would they be
about even talking about what they're
about but informative would be sharing
a proposition or some
reducing someone's uncertainty about the
state of something in the world i'm
feeling this way or that weighs this
much
and so on
for other statements because indeed
they're defined by the content
and their structure
so ecologically
remy what might these
types of
speech behaviors be doing
oh yeah these
these the types of acts of language are
are well accounted for in
in the transmission view but there are
some questions that remain about the
imperative form of communication because
uh it's
it's
not clear that
imperative communication can be
understood as a form of transmission of
content because
we have the feeling that when we uh
comment something or we request
something we are not um
transmitting information or we are not
uh
aiming at changing the the mental states
of the person that we are talking to we
are aiming at making them do something
in the world directly so so there's
there's kind of a a mismatch there it
seems
um so obviously uh
the the the people in the transmission
view will have an answer they will say
that like uh when i have some for
instance that desire or the intention
that something is the case i then
an imperative act of communication is my
transmitting this intention or this
desire to the person who then has this
desire or this intention and then can
bring about the the state of affairs
that i i intend to achieve
but it's not
i'm not sure obviously you can delve in
the details but i'm not sure that's
exactly what we want to do when we uh
state when we produce an imperative
active language obviously we we want
uh we just don't just want that the
person has the intention of doing
something we want the the the thing done
in the world so i i believe that the
imperatives kind of communication is not
really well accounted for in the
transmission view
and what's interesting is that in a way
the imperative form of communication is
like the basic form of communication in
our framework because um that what what
a communication is is uh acting through
the behavior of somebody else by
affecting its field of affordance so
we can
we can go back to like the the forms of
animal communication that we described
earlier in the paper and these are all
can all be considered to be impressive
forms of community or proto-imperative
forms of communication so that's like
the starting point
um uh and we we achieve these acts on
the behavior of somebody else by
altering their field of affordances to
make them some do something
but uh how do we account for information
informative uh active communication and
an idea that we put forward in the paper
is that
um
in format the the kind of
acts of communication that that we
consider to be informative will be
acts that aim to construct or alter a
shared field of affordances in
in a way that is more durable than just
an immediate imperative act of language
so what we are doing we are changing the
layout of the the the context that we
take for to be relevant to our joint
action and these these changing of
affordances do not have to be
immediately acted upon i can say oh
there's something in the in the context
that's relevant it does not necessarily
call for action immediately but it's
something that is like in the background
of our context of action and so it's
change it changes the shared field of
affordance but it's not
directly um
soliciting an action from the
interlocutor as would be the case for
the imperative act of language so in a
way um
it's like as if uh
in the beginning an informative active
language is like a a long-term
imperative or a dispositional imperative
we put something in the context we say
oh that's relevant we can act on it at
some point but it's not necessarily
immediately to be acted upon so that's
how we can like put the the the idea
that okay we can change our context of
action
what we take to be relevant in the
context of action and
we can come back to it later when when
it's relevant and act on it but it's not
something that is to be acted upon
immediately and so that's like the the
the the
the difference uh between imperative and
formative begins to to to be
discerned there where an imperative is
like i'm i'm saying that this so this
affordance should be acted upon
immediately and informative is like i'm
putting this in the context it changes
the layout of affordances i so for
instance
there would be
i don't know how to come up with an
example but if i inform you of something
i'm putting
i'm changing the layout of the
affordance that we take for for granted
in the context of our interaction and it
changes uh in the long term the
interaction and it can like drive the
interaction in various ways but it's not
something to be acted uh directly
immediately so that's the the the basic
distinction and that's like the the
beginning of a distinction between
informative and imperative
and i can say a few words about
interrogative too
so as we said um
uh and and communication is acting
typically acting through the behavior of
somebody else
by by
by uh altering its field of affordance
and interrogative uh it's interesting
because it's exactly the distinction
between between imperative and
interrogative is uh really similar to
the distinction between pragmatic value
and epistemic value in active inference
so for instance when we produce an
action that aims to maximize uh
pragmatic value we are trying to for
instance to um
to
make the state of the world correspond
to a prediction of our generative model
and when we uh make something which is
guided by epistemic value what we try to
do is we're trying to reduce in certain
uncertainty about our our niche for
instance but so
in a way so for instance when i'm eating
something i'm i'm
maximizing my uh my my pragmatic value
because i'm uh for instance reducing a
prediction error that time i'm hungry
and i want to so that's like a basic
example so but when i'm exploring my
environment when i'm making a visual
decade to
explore my niche so that would be an
epistemic uh
action so to speak so interrogative acts
of language are exactly analog to
epistemic actions but they are epistemic
actions through the behavior of somebody
else so instead of for instance by
myself exploring the niche exploring the
field of affordance i can produce this
act that will make the other person this
close to me an element of the field of
affordance that um
can then reduce my uncertainty about
what is the context of our action so
that's really the distinction between
imperative and interrogative is really
to be understood along the line of the
distinction between pragmatic value and
epistemic value so that's
a beginning to an introduction to these
these distinctions in the
in the types of acts of language
thanks tommy you totally you totally
read my mind there about like what i
wanted to to
elaborate on even though my question was
like very poorly framed um yeah i think
that that's very useful for um
especially in like the goal directed
aspect of um imperative versus
interrogative or informative like what
how how they interact with our maybe are
we don't have a joint goal versus we do
have a joint goal or the goal is to
develop some shared state of a shared
mental state
so that was really helpful thank you
another note is that the informative
behavior
is like the base class of the
transmission view
because it seems to be like it's
updating one on the details like what if
i'm saying there is a gallon of milk in
the fridge
truly what else could be conveyed other
than the content so it seems like the
most natural and then there's specific
kinds of content like um
sharing the content that you have a
question or sharing the content that you
would like somebody to act and so in
that way
as you described
many forms of speech behavior are well
accounted for in the transmission view
and that accounting is actually kind of
a callback to
that math stream for with david spivak
about accounting systems so these are
like accounting models
um
and then you
highlighted that the imperative
in the inactive and ecological
view on communication
that the imperative is perhaps the basic
form of communication and that can be
seen developmentally
through a
child and the kinds of communications
that they might engage in
as well as from an evolutionary
perspective with the kinds of audio or
chemical or physical stigmargy and marks
that different kinds of creatures use to
communicate within and across species so
those are action-oriented
communications
as we can then say all action-oriented
communication
or all communication
we can say is action-oriented in an
analogous way so then imperative becomes
the base class
shaping the field of affordances if
that's what the ecological view on
communication is
is going to be most natural with kinds
of expressions that we can say are
imperative
and then
informative updates
are like one step removed from direct
action requests
so saying turn the handle to the left
is an imperative
if you said
i'm going to inform you about two things
the handle can be turned to the left and
if this happens you may want to turn the
handle those are breaking down a
capacity for action
into sequential or modular or
recomposable
statements
but those statements are like hiding
the consequences of action
and so in that way we we can have an
action-oriented view on communication
and then see different kinds of other
behavior
as like
modified or
truncated or censored or hidden
action
modification
and that may or may not entail needing
to even explain
how meaning is represented transmitted
or received
yes remy
oh yeah and uh that that's exactly it so
the
that's really the the
the idea explained it very well and
another example that we that we often
use with here is the
the joint action of uh cooking a meal
with various people so like we an
example we used in the last discussion
the example of moving a couch so another
example maybe to to change a bit our
intuitions about communication so with
people cooking a meal together we can
suppose that some people uh some of the
suppose that we're in the kitchen of one
of the the person and the other doesn't
know exactly where all the things are
and so a person the person could say
there's flour in the in the
in the cupboard or in the pantry and
saying that that's an information
informative active language but that
could that's like that might be a hidden
imperative
in so far as at some point in the
interaction in the cooking of the meal
the the flower might be needed and at
this point this alteration of the field
of affordances this appearance of the
flower as an affordance and that is in
the context might drive the action of
the person when the flower is needed at
a certain point the person will have
this affordance in its field and will uh
go to to to seek it if it's necessary at
that point so the informative is as i
said something like an a dispositional
or long-term imperative
some something of a hidden imperative uh
that can drive behavior in the long term
so so it's like at the beginning this
distinction is more or less
a distinction of like is this affordance
to be acted upon
immediately by you or is it posed in the
context and can like alter the dynamic
without being directly acted upon
immediately so that's how the the basic
distinction is drawn and yeah i i think
that that's that's how we try to to
account for informative uh
without
describing it as uh transmitting a
content or an information uh so so
that's that's the idea and i think that
you explain it very well uh in your in
your
in your your
yeah
in your explanation
good yeah it's very
interesting it's just another
consequence of centering action
so many things that the pragmatic turn
pragmatism
earlier than the so-called pragmatic
turn in the
neurosciences and all of the
developments in cognitive science
in many cases it's been like
an information or an inference view
yielding to an action view
and that has just played out differently
on different frontiers
and it feels like in a way language is
like
the stronghold
of information views
because it's like so amenable to
syntactic and discourse analysis
in a and compositionality
and all these features that we see in
formal models and in computer systems
that it feels like oh maybe all the
funny stuff that people do and say
we'll figure that one out
too
blue and then dean
so i just wonder about um
like mimicry
which is something that we see like in
the animal kingdom a lot um and like
whether that is uh imperative i mean
sometimes i guess it can be imperative
like
um watch me do this and then you do it
but but not always some so sometimes
it's like
um you know an animal will see another
animal do something and then they try it
too right and and so what um i don't
know i just don't know how to like
in the terms of teaching and learning
and like shared goal directedness like
what is maybe the role of mimicry and
how does that like what is the effect on
the field of affordances does it just
open up like you see someone do
something and then your field of
affordances opens to that is also
possible for me or does that not have
maybe like a semantic analog i don't
know
yeah that's a really good question and
often people
who
adopt the transmission view will uh
adopt the view that the the main driver
of the evolution of language
in human societies was the transmitting
of uh of knowledge and of skills for
instance and of of uh various types of
activities so that's like a
a clear example where it seems that the
transmission view has a story to say
uh
when
if we if we take for granted that like
imitating somebody or or
or learning something to somebody is in
effect transmitting a knowledge or a a a
certain kind of of uh of mental state or
coming to cognitive states so that
there's clearly
something interesting there for the
transmission view but i think that's an
an alternative possible analysis you
just heard uh
at it is the idea that you you
when you're interacting with somebody
and for specifically with somebody of
you of your own species seeing this
person do something
can open new affordances for yourself
for instance if i say i see somebody
that looks like me do something
i'm i have learned that when
somebody like look looks like me does
something usually maybe with a little
bit of effort i can do it too so
do somebody doing something is a way of
opening opening up new affordances for
me and trying to achieve it so
in in many cases mimicry will not
necessarily be communicative that is
because an organism can do something
without having no
is not communicating nothing to anybody
but it happens that somebody else
watches it and
imitates it so in that case there's not
necessarily
a communication but in cases where there
is communication involved i think we can
analyze indeed analyze it
just as you said that is saying that
the action of the organism opens up a
new affordance for
the the the person who's watching it
doing it and usually in cases of
explicit uh
skill learning for instance the the the
expert will like do the thing more
deliberately more slowly more explicitly
to like uh show what are the relevant
movement that has to be made in order to
achieve so that's like
making more salient the kind of of uh of
movement that have to be made to uh to
uh to succeed in in
in performing the skill so i think
that's a a way that we can understand
this kind of skill learning in the
transformation of the affordances that
are available to the person that's
receiving the uh the communication
that's how i would i i think i would
analyze it
one
simple uh example kind of building on
this making certain actions deliberate
then
dean
interested for your thoughts
even showing something deliberately
verbally calling attention or just the
position of the body for a physical
skill
it shapes the field of affordances
specifically where somebody can look
so if you're like okay i'm going to
swing the bat and then now i'm going to
show you what my hand you know this
isn't usually how i do it but now i'm
going to show you how i was holding it
at that time
you have shaped their field of ocular
motor affordances in and that is what
enables their generative model to update
and so
nowhere in that account
is i'm transmitting that this is to be
held between these two fingers
let alone counter factuals like here's
what you do if your hand is slippery
but
by bodily posture
including vocal box bodily posture
we can have an integrated account of
mimicry skill transfer
again transfers playing way too strongly
into a transmission view but um
skill resonance or something similar
that helps recognize the cognitive
entities
learning process
dean
um okay well i want to take what you're
saying but i'm going to put a little bit
of a weird flex on it because i want to
try to combine
blues pin and remy's pin and daniel's
pin into one kind of question
that comes back to the paper so like the
last five minutes of the conversation
has been focused on
the act of and as typing when it
pertains to language and communication
and and blue bringing mimicry in is a is
a form of as
versus a lot of the emphasis in the
paper which is on the of
of communication and language so here's
my question
i went back and read the paper again and
i caught myself asking what do i hear
when i'm reading something or i'm
listening to someone what do i hear
as both processor and the producer
as we mentioned off-camera an arranger
of something
being signaled which i'm picking up on
and decoding
so
rather than just leave it there i'll
park that for a second because i think
that's the the
the nut of what i want to ask
as a processor and a producer as an
arranger i can hear things in mono
i can hear things in stereo i can even
hear things if i go to my apple music in
spatial audio
so
that is a field of affordances a
question as opposed to a source
of affordances question and if i only
limit myself to the source i'm going to
be asking only of
type questions
right
so
if i want to stay in the as of if i want
to be able to hold up two things at once
at a minimum the stereo or the spatial
that's when i get into the ecological
even if it's
specific ecological because i'm not
collapsing down to
a single source
as my point of contact
which then asks leads me to ask the fact
that communication can be formed as and
of types meaning
mono stereo spatial
mimicry interrogation the fact that it
can be broken out into those things does
that introduce
self-production
into the self-processing
in your paper
because i know there's a heavy emphasis
on the of
on the
processing
but i wonder
if you keep the as when blue brings it
up or when daniel brings it up
if we're if we're keeping it on that
even a specific ecological level
are we not when we hear something
producers
as well
what are we producing
i i have no idea but i know i hear
something even when i i read what you're
typing oh i'm not just hearing the
tapity tap
i'm hearing something we are proud
to produce
we are producing like it's changing i'm
hearing that
not
reading that
so if i incorporate that
what am i doing and i'm not the expert
on communication so i wonder what the
expert can tell me about them
yeah that's a good question
um
yeah
i'm not sure what to say about that
blue first and then we'll continue
so i wonder if um what you're hearing
dean has anything to do with
the internal monologue right so like as
you are reading something then you are
also hearing something right and so it's
like there's this internal i mean
like i have a very i'm a talker person
and so i like i have a strong internal
monologue like all the time running like
even getting ready in the morning okay i
need to get my shoes and get my purse
and my keys and i have to pack my lunch
and like all these things right like
that happen so i'm constantly hearing
that like as if i'm saying it maybe to
myself even though i'm not speaking but
but i wonder what um
you know so i definitely am a producer
of whatever i'm reading like i reproduce
it i i reproduce it though right so i
reproduce it in my own mind my own
internal monologue but i wonder like i
know not everyone has this internal
monologue and so so what is it then the
same
for the people that don't perhaps have
this internal monologue and maybe they
carry around a picture of all the things
that they need to get ready in the
morning so yeah
justine
yeah and i think you bring up a good
point blue
is it a monologue is it a stereolog
is it a quadrophonic log
for some people i mean i mean there was
an availability way back when maybe
even before some of you were born there
was quadrophonic sound i remember the
who album and quadrophonic sound and
like
to my
simple ears i didn't understand
what that even meant just because they
were able to break it out into four
parts it didn't didn't change what i was
both producing and processing
so
but but the fact that we can type it
like that like not type it out but
literally turn it into types
is the part where i don't really have
the background to be able to explain
how that that ability that field of
affordances as opposed to examining this
as a single source of affordance
changes
the the communication gain because it
does it certainly does speak to mimicry
and what we can and cannot pick up it
certainly speaks to daniel's point
about
about what happens when when layers
appear and disappear because we narrow
down
what we're picking up on versus have
have both of our ears working even
though we think it's our eyes
that are doing all the circadian right
so again i'm not i'm not trying to
ask the impossible question i'm just
curious in the sense of producer
and processor
and what that arrangement is
dependent upon what the what because
daniel brought it up in the in the last
live stream circumstances matter
so but as a hearer
i i wonder i wonder if we if we if we
know enough about ourselves
to really be able to to to give this
anything more than it is
as remy kindly pointed out in the paper
give this more than
sort of a a big road map
view
if we if we are taking context into
consideration
thank you remy
yeah i think the discussion about uh
internal monologue is really interesting
and there's a lot of i think that you
said the dean that orders i think really
interesting but the i want to go back to
the the the idea of the the monologue
and
there are some people who believe that
like chomsky you believe that um
language is not even for communication
it's about structuring thought and so
there's there are people who believe
that the language is uh first and
foremost something that
is a property of the structure of our
thoughts and not a property of systems
of communication and
so
there's this idea that
like the
the the
the inner monologue comes first and then
comes the communication of this inner
monologue in the in in in communication
so
we have this basically that is once uh
once more
inherent in the the transmission view
that we have our train of thought we are
we have our our uh
the the the inner speech that we that we
have in our heads and then we translate
this in our speech in uh overt speech
that is then uh taken by somebody else
and
i i think that this gets the the the the
priority wrong between outer speech and
inner speech and there's been a lot of
work in philosophy by uh notably wilfrid
sellers and
by others in
in psychology like vygotsky uh who say
that the the first form of speech is
overt speech that is then internalized
in in
that becomes like um
that becomes inner but first in the
beginning there's only over speech
a child that learns language does not
have an inner speech there's only outer
speech that is expressed directly the
child speaks the child
do things with his words in its
environment and does not directly
automatically as the uh corresponding
inner monologue in its head and there's
a process that's really interesting i
think
that is uh that where we see that
beginning to happen where the child
speaks to itself alone when there's
nobody else around and so there's this
transition where language is used in
communicative interaction and at some
point the child use
language alone and there's a question of
why why does it do and and i think that
our view of communication is really uh
um interestingly uh linked with views of
uh of uh inner monologue as self-cueing
or self-regulation and so the the the
child can
uh author regulate its field of
affordance when it's alone uh when
there's nobody else around and in time
this inner the outer uh
zone
for instance this outer monologue but
alone monologue uh becomes overt because
the the child learns to not necessarily
produce the the the sound that
correspond to the producing of these
acts and there's there's this
integration that's there's this
internalization of
outdoor discourse that becomes inner
discourse and there's a lot of
cute anecdotes about that my nephew is i
i i have a nephew the son of my my
sister and he's like when he's uh he's
uh about to go to sleep he's in his bed
and uh
every night he's like we are saying the
events that happened in the day and he's
saying like the the
the comments that that he the the rules
the norms that he heard in the day oh i
don't have to do that i must do that and
so he's like we are saying what happened
in the day so that this outer monologue
when he's alone in his bed is like the
beginning of inner thought we're seeing
is thoughts uh uh out in the open and at
some point this inner this outer
monologue will become internalized and
we we won't hear the his his thoughts uh
out in the open but i think that's like
the process that it takes
and there's also the idea at another
point that we we for instance when we
read or usually we read uh silently so
we we read what's written and we have
the the corresponding inner monologue
but it's known that in ancient times
when people were reading usually they
were reading automatically a lot
loud loudly and they it took a training
in order to be able to read without
speaking the words uh uh and so so like
in in middle age and then i i'm not
perfectly sure it's if it's it's
historically accurately we we should
verify it but i i believe that's that's
true
it seems that i heard that so it seems
that first there's the outer monologue
the outer
dialogue and then there's the outer
monologue and then there's the inner
monologue that comes after that and i
think that's more the the the true
direction of priority between
inner monologue and outer monologue
blue
so i just have a cute anecdote
about about learning learning to talk so
i have two kids and they're super
different um my son did as your nephew
did remy like would be in his crib
talking to himself talking to his
stuffed animals and kind of recreating
events right right in in a similar way
he also babbled a lot like a lot of like
just always
like just saying nothing from the time
he was tiny um and has an incredible
vocabulary i mean now he's six but
people are like wow how old is this kid
i mean he's reading at three and just
that is like very very verbal
and my my daughter is super different so
she did not really babble but she signed
like crazy and they they both went to
the same school they both teach them the
same signs like to have say milk and
cracker and cheese and you know bathroom
and all the things right so so like they
both went to the same daycare same niche
environment and she picked up the
signing much more than my son ever did
he used maybe one or two signs she's
like 20. like i had to go learn the
signs
and before she could sign she would just
like stand in the kitchen and scream
like just unable to communicate whatever
it was that she wanted
and it it's so odd like they're they're
just like two totally different kids but
she when she was learning chinese um i
had a parent-teacher conference with the
tea and like they've both been learning
trainees now they're in private school
they've been learning for like eight
years so when she was first starting to
learn she wouldn't speak in class and
the teacher and i had a conference and
the teacher said like i am concerned
about your daughter she doesn't
participate in class like she doesn't
have to take chinese it's not mandatory
if you wanted to put her in a different
class or she could have a silent reading
period and i was like
oh
so it occurred to me like and i knew
that she and because she didn't babble
and like i was somebody handed her a
lollipop she was like two and she i said
say thank you and she did the sign for
it but but i mean she really did not
speak like would not form clear words
unless she knew she could say them
perfectly
and so i sent her to tutoring with the
chinese tutor like just twice three
times and then it began like so she was
like listening can i repeat this can i
engage with this word correctly and and
she just was very more much more careful
in that but both kids as soon as they
could talk talked in their sleep like
crazy
anyway there's my cute story
nice stories
the development of the self-cueing
and self-speaking is very
interesting
even
earlier on in behavioral
analysis and behaviorism
like in bf skinner's work there's
extensive
exploration of how covert
monologues and covert speech and
societies of mind
and then i guess more recently it's
become better understood how
electrical activity in the body and in
the brain are still
initiated during covert speech
like it's not an audible speech but
actually in various ways it still is
embodied
and then
this question of reading perhaps is
another
area
where
we're talking about in this language
area
what is similar or different with
listening to speech participating in
speech
audibly
is it different if it's read or braille
how does the modality
and the media influence
some of these things dean
um
again i i think the proportions of two
ears to one mouth is something that we
need to kind of really
hold on to in this idea of single source
and monologue versus
what potentially is a stereo log in a
field of affordances as opposed to a
single source um
i don't know why why we've been i don't
know what advantages are are given by
having as an ability to hear in stereo
but they must be
better than having a single ear or a
single receipt a single reception site
and and yet we we don't have two mouths
so i again i i think it's
understandable why from a
transmission point of view the deliverer
standpoint we always collapse back to
a source a single source but if we flip
that and now think about it from the
receiving standpoint
how does that how does that change our
sense of what communication is because
it doesn't change if i cover one of my
ears or if i have an earbud and it
cancels
and yet something fundamentally must
change in terms of communication and the
joint action even if it's monologue
in my own head versus dialogue or trial
log or quadrilog now again i haven't
done any research to try to try to
figure out what other people have done
in terms of looking at that but to your
point though renee in terms of let's get
let's even get past transmission
we're getting trying to get past the
idea of what is being delivered
and being and trying to gain a deeper
appreciation
of what is being heard
so
blue i i'll tell you a little story um
i have a loquacious son he's in his 30s
now but he's actually as he's gotten
smarter and wiser speaks less
like occasionally he gets out of
developing word silence that could serve
an entire community
and
i find that really fascinating i don't
have to comment on it it's just you
notice that as people know more
they
maybe they sign more maybe they find
other ways
to
to make their point and it goes back to
that time in your take thing
so
yeah
great um there's so many
references like the true way is the one
that can't be spoken of or
those who do do and those who can't
teach all these kinds of funny um
you know poking fun at different
archetypes and so on and how that's
related to wisdom
the two ears and one mouth
which you've been referencing throughout
the conversations and the quadrophonic
sound quadrophenia i'm sure it was
amazing
um
it is
true that the enrichment
and the spatial
nature
of heard
sounds soundscapes
is uh
it's like something that can't be turned
off
like the receiver all of our receiving
is bilateral
visual
nostrils and smell
proprioceptive is heavily multilateral
it's it's but it's it has a coarse
bilateral symmetry
but
um
the mouth as our action states
needs generative
uh cohesion
perhaps just to just so story but i
don't know of any cases where there are
um
now there are some bodily sounds that
are bilateral like perhaps the um
vibration of a cricket
so it's not that like sound production
can't be bilateral
it's just that wherever sound production
is localized
on the sender
when we when we highlight content in its
transmission
where does that account begin what has
to begin with the content and the
representation in the sender
and then you could ask whether it was um
fully or partially or deceptively
recognized by the recipients potentially
when we center the recipient's action
but even calling them a recipient kind
of puts them onto a back foot we're just
centering the agent's engagement
ecologically
and they're interfacing with fields of
affordances
then we we do see that
stereophonic enrichments
of
everything
and no matter how narrow or
um how many shannon
bits
or kolmogorov bits it doesn't really
matter
because it's going to be unpacked in a
generative model
that brings in
aspects that
aren't and don't need to be in the
signal and hence
aren't or don't need to be in our
account of the signaling
just think i'm trying to bring back the
inference into the active inference here
because the active part is definitely
the transmission piece
so you know thank you for for
reinforcing that
but i i do
i do wonder when we do bring the
inference back
why
are our
sensing accordances
are those bilateral
forms there must be some advantage
to that and so is it as blue pointed out
because of as
not just the heavy emphasis on the of
what what was the product of my
transmission
how am i pulling in
this communication and what advantages
are there
to
not getting strung out or hung up on the
mono
log the single
source
one thing that makes me think about is
in
caricature disinfo representations of
bug vision insect vision it will look
like they're seeing many separate
cells
whereas if one were just to take a
breath and think about their own visual
experience we don't see two
fields of view
so it's like not really making sense why
an insect would see
multiple
so
the visual field
because there's quote objects out there
we have all these different ways that we
can talk about how we know that we're
experiencing an integrated generative
model like the blind spot the
differences in visual acuity in the
peripheral vision color vision in the
periphery ocular motor circades and the
way that attention is uh suppressed
during cicading so that it's not causing
this nausea all these features are
really important and they point beyond a
photon transmission view a vision
into this generative
stereophonic vision
and then in the audio
setting
having
multiple
oral
uh orifices
and also even covering them up like
they're still transduction through the
skull and so on um
we are also seeking to flesh out a
generative model of
sounds in our environment
so if we cover our ears
like that proprioception
will help us understand that even if
something sounds kind of quiet we
actually we can recognize that it's
still a loud noise
or if we have one ear in a pillow
we could recognize
that something is happening even though
if it is being heard differently on both
sides
um
so
having multiple sensors
is very compatible
with a unified generative model
experience because it forces one
to abstract beyond any sensor reading
if you have one midline thermometer
then
that's your point estimate for
temperature
or you could have like a gaussian blur
like i'm just less confident about the
temperature further from my one central
sensor but maybe i'm maybe it's a tight
gaussian maybe it's very broad but this
is the best estimate
why would i have any other estimate
centered anywhere else
when you have two thermometers
now there's a generative modeling
question about whether it's going to be
a gaussian with a peak in the middle or
whether you're going to have a peak more
on one side and have it just go through
the other depending on those sensor
readings
but at that point you're ending up with
some distributions
which if we think of that distribution
as like what is experienced as like
maybe the product of the sensing process
that distribution's enrichment
is of a different type
and yet of a different simplicity
than any number of sensor readings
in terms of what their raw information
are so it seems very
relevant this two ears one mouth
not just for listening twice as much as
we speak
but for
listening twice as actively as we speak
or something like that
what do you think about census remy
yeah i think i think that you
you explained it well
uh it's
right yeah i think it's useful as you
said to have multiple
sensory channels that can be active
because i think that's an argument from
how we and it's uh in its book in 2013
book on the predictive uh the predictive
mind i think he says that uh
if you have a um
a tribunal and you're trying to
establish the for instance the the
culpability of the
of a convict you you hope that you have
multiple independent sources of
information because if these sources of
information are influenced each other
you have a less reliable uh
how do you say
i i forget the world uh timonty manage
in english so i i forgot the word but
you have a less reliable
information about the about the
the the
the
the case so like it's useful from
from a reliability standpoint to to have
multiple independent uh sorts of
information so so that that may be an
explanation of why we have uh
that may be an explanation of their
their also their relative modularity of
perception so there are we know that
there are great limits to that
modularity but there is a certain degree
of independence
from in the the different uh
sensory modalities that we have
um so yeah about the the two here is
obviously i i think maybe if we had if
um our auditory uh sensory system was
only devised to a communicative
interaction maybe it would be okay to
just have one here one ear because we
could like we we know who's talking to
us and so we can direct our our um
our sensory uh apparatus toward this
communicative
signal but because we use our our ears
not just to to attune to a communicative
interaction but also to know what's in
our surrounding it's really clearly more
useful to have
to to have a great
reception from from information for
anywhere around us so i i maybe if if
audition was only about communication
it would be okay to have just one ear
but because we want to know as precisely
what's happening there uh and at the
same time know what's happening there
maybe it's it's uh it has been more
useful to have these two here's two
years on both sides so so maybe that
there's something about that
yeah one short note and then dean is
there are also
animals with anatomy so that they can
direct their ears which is seemingly
very analogous to the ocular motor
circadine it's like an audio succeed and
it just the human form outside of the
ear wiggling which is maybe slightly
vestigial representation of that but we
have opted for a strategy
with fixed ear positioning but a mobile
neck which also makes circades so that's
kind of our low speed
audio um
dean
yeah i think the only advantage i could
see having two miles is that i could eat
the french fries and drink the milkshake
at the same time and i don't know what
that would be like it was just
overpowering but what i think is
interesting in in the dot dot one
um blue brought up the idea of so
how do we make sure that there's a
difference between content
and context and i think whether it's two
eyes
two ears two nostrils whatever there
must be some advantage to the form
because as i said even if you cover one
of those
intakes
it's not just a redundancy issue it's a
recursion issue it creates that ability
to
see context hear context and smell
context i don't believe we would have
those things
and as i said i think i'd get
overwhelmed with the context of having
both french fries and milkshake
it would just blow me up so
but that that's just the
thing
that says this little self thing do not
give people two mouths it can be
overpowering
one aspect might return us to the
question of
compositionality
it seems like visual
composition and temporal composition
in music and in
heard
speech as
speaking in terms of
generative models
have highly factorizable or sparsely
connected generative models
famously connected to like the where and
the what streams in visual neuroanatomy
and that's been explored in some active
inference papers with awareness and
whatness as being
factorizable in the generative model
because it really is the case that
different layers
can host different what's and so it
makes sense to like have those two
totally separate
um
taste and smell
which are um
[Music]
they're more midlined though there are
two nostrils i'm not totally sure on on
whether there's like you know one or two
smell chambers or anything
composition of
chemical
bouquets
seems quite different
like two paintings that you like next to
each other
or two songs in succession that you like
or it's a little bit different
than to
smells or tastes sequentially or
composed
um
[Music]
and so maybe these more
uh sometimes called basal sensory or
cognitive features
are less effable
and this kind of relates to a
a cognitive
stack
where
verbal
and symbolic communication is
like the tip of the iceberg
supported by
biological processes that are
differently or less effortable
and at first only pointed towards like
through metaphors in speech
butterflies in my stomach and so on but
then ultimately entirely inexpressible
maybe with some stop in between like
being able to express through the body
like what it's like to do a certain
bodily position
um or have a certain experience or be in
a certain physiological state
um
and
this kind of casts a light on the
transmission view
um complementing the ecological view
the transmission view
is like down propagating
symbolic communication
and seeking for that to apply all the
way on down
whereas a more bottom-up and arguably
eco-evo devo informed perspective
is grounded in
the ecological
setting
and then allows for
the crystallization of symbolic
processes
including communicated symbolic
processes which are aren't they supposed
to be the stronghold of the transmission
view
but then
if
even that
phenomena
can be captured within an ecological
frame
then there's an extremely strong basis
for the the integrative cohesion of an
ecological view
as opposed to an extremely piecemeal
and um
question begging
transmission view
like we talked about semiosis and
biosymmiosis in livestream 47
so will we see
um verbal communication and behavior
as something that is enabled and with
analogy but not the same as
cellular transduction
or are we going to seek a cellular
transduction explanation
based on verbal behavior
let's return to some of our topics
alright few areas to go blue
any thoughts just anywhere you want
yeah so i just wanted to follow up on
what you um said and i just think that
the beauty of the ecological approach to
understanding communication is
that communication between cells be it
semiotic representation or other and
between animals maybe with gestures
maybe inter-species communication like
you know you tell your cat come here and
the cat comes or dog or whatever so i
think that that the ability to model
systems
like all systems it is very um
important like if if the transmission
view is not capable of representing all
of the situations from cell to cell
communication to human to dog
communication and
and all along the line um i i think that
maybe uh it's
in the way that the fep and active
inference is scale free and and like
doesn't have but i mean it's it's across
any hierarchical temporal
cognitive scale
i think that that the way that we view
communication also needs to be broadly
applicable
yes remy
so yeah that's uh that's the aim
but clearly
some people will say that
sophisticated linguistic communication
cannot be
accounted for in terms of
in terms of ecological communication
because
as daniel said the symbolic
communication
characteristic of language seems to be
too removed from the kind of basic
interaction described by the ecological
approach so there's this like
there's a lot of work to be done still
to to really explain these the the
high-level linguistic interactions that
we have in order in terms of uh
of the ecological and active
communication but uh yeah there's
another example of um of communication
uh
as you said
we can account maybe for uh a
communicative interaction between cells
but there's also there's been work on
communication between between plants and
how plants perceive their their
environment in terms of affordances
there's been work on that and so i think
that there's a it's just to say that
there's an it's another uh and another
way in which we can develop the
ecological approach um
it seems that
that if we
yeah
any any um
any organisms that organism that behaves
so any organism will have a field of
affordance and
it seems that if
it wants to
act on other organisms its environment
it will act in uh affecting its you know
field of affordance and
it looks like uh the the kind of
communication that is that play between
trees for instance which
alerts each other
about uh for instance the
threats in in the in the forest or uh
sources of uh of uh useful uh resources
in the in the ground so these kinds of
modifications of uh uh
of the of the uh of them
yeah of the
i don't know how are exactly the
mechanisms by which these the
the these uh these
these communication take place but we
can also see them as modifications of
the field of affordances of three so i
think that that was when i saw that i
was really
i thought it was really cool that the
trees behaved at a really really slower
time scale obviously but like behave
when they they go when they they send
like their their roots in certain
directions and things like that we can
see it as them exploring their
environment and
reacting to a field of affordance that
that day so obviously that that's also
uh controversial because there there's
all this debate about the cognitive
states of uh of plants and or do they
have a
consciousness or that thing but i think
that we can say that they probably have
something like a field of affordance and
it seems that they can
communicate with each other uh
via these modifications of their field
of affordance without us having to say
that they are transmitting content which
would be really weird
from
the standpoint of a plant
thank you blue
so just
i like if you haven't seen the plant
robot created by the mit media lab like
check it out because the plant like they
connected it to a set of wheels and a
motor and literally will wheel itself
back and forth from window to window
like searching for sunlight so so i mean
when you modify the field of affordances
of a plant it will it will take
advantage of of those affordances for
movement or or um any other kind of
thing and as to the the complexity of um
like linguistic communication okay but
like also like the complexity of
cellular communication especially in
like developmental biology and all of
the growth factors and signaling cues
and i mean it's highly complex and like
the recombinatorial aspect is also
incredibly crazy like i i think
it would take a lot to convince me that
linguistic communication is
more sophisticated or more advanced
than biological communication in a
developing organism i'm not sold on that
thanks dean
can you can you help me understand a
little bit more about the um
the influence
uh in the joint action if
if i'm in madrid
um
a lot of people who are trying to get my
attention
i'm not very
i'm not i don't speak spanish very well
just barely get by and so a lot of times
things are spoken to me
and there there is a there seems to be a
break in terms of the amount of sensing
i get
and so that joint action
could you maybe especially in the light
of that earlier uh converse part where
you talked about young kids
they think they it appears they're
talking to themselves
but they're talking to the world and
maybe they're not influencing the world
but they would like to could you maybe
talk about that sort of sensing side of
that joint action
yeah so i think that's what uh kids that
talk alone are doing they're not they
they learn to talk by talking to each
other and affecting other persons but
when they learn to talk to each other
what they're doing they're they're
influencing themselves i think that
that's the the part about self-cueing so
what they're doing they're they're
they're modifying their own field of
affordances with their uh with their
this this inner speech and that's how
they they learn to self-cue and
self-regulate themselves by bringing
some uh
some images in mind or things like that
so that's the i think that's what
happens when
when
a child uh learns to to to speak alone
um there's obviously a lot more to say
about that um
when so so the question of the
of
different languages when you're in
another country and you don't
uh you so you you're spoken to and you
you're not
understanding correctly but you you pick
up some some parts of what's said so i
think that um
i think that the the learning of a
language is often um is often understood
as the the the
as uh
as uh um learning a code so learning a
set of associations between uh um
between um
meanings and between uh forms uh that
can be uh either written or spoken but i
think that in the the the approach that
we're uh we're advancing here uh
learning a language is really more like
learning learning a skill so you're
learning to to speak and learning to
understand and interact correctly in a
given language as you're learning to do
anything else you're learning to play a
game you're learning to like play hockey
so or play a soccer or whatever it's the
is the the same kind of learning and
you're learning to interact in that kind
of game
and
probably there's a similarity between
various languages um
because it's
there's there's a similarity
there's the yeah like like very
i would i could talk about wittgenstein
once once again but like there's this
the
various languages uh
resemble each other because they have
this this family resemblance so because
you have this familiarity with
speaking in a language even when you're
in another place where you don't
understand the language you have a basic
grasp of some of the structures of the
game that is being played and so from
the context you can get uh understand
some of the things that are said
understand understand some of the things
that are expected of you
because you have this grasp of what a
kind of game is played when we speak a
language and so even if you're in in um
in another country when you don't speak
the language from the context that in
which you find yourself you may be able
to piece some things together uh
obviously if you're like uh just in a
place with absolutely no context you're
in a
a white room completely empty and
somebody's talking to you you have no
context probably you won't understand
anything but if you're in a context
where you can understand that some kinds
of
there's some some goals that are uh that
are in place and some people's around
you are trying to achieve some goal you
can apply your understanding of the game
that you play in your own language to
this new language and so you can get
some things
you can understand some things about
what's what's what you have to do and uh
how you should behave and how you can
respond but
i think that that's a better way of
understanding the kind of limited
understanding that you have in this kind
of of interactions rather than in you
having a code of your language and then
you try to apply this code in this you i
think that that the
the idea of learning a skill learning
how to play a game is a better analogy
to understanding how you you come to
learn a language and how you come to
apply this this long knowledge in other
contexts where the language that is
spoken is not the same that you that
you're mastering does that kind of
confirm that it couldn't be content
first
that it would have to be context
bound
yeah
in my view the the the context is a
central element in in
in any communicative interaction in any
cooperative communicative interaction i
think it's the
in the context what what i i call the
context in the paper appears as a shared
field of affordance so that that's the
the the affordance that are present in
the in the the the
in the environmental
context in which you find yourself in
with the other person and that that's
that's
this element that often pre-exists the
communicative interaction is there a
great great source of constraint on the
the communicative interaction so yeah
when you're you you come to speak with
somebody you're
almost never like in a absolutely
context-free uh place you're always in a
restaurant in uh
in i don't know in the bus in the in
in at the grocery store you're somewhere
and there's this basic set of
affordances that are shared that you
understand that you can do this you
cannot do that and this this set of
constraints offered by this shared field
of affordances really drives and
constrains how the communicative
interaction will unfold so that i think
that even if you're in another country
often the the context will be hard to
pick up but some sometimes there will be
shared context that you can get a grasp
on
and that you can uh
that can favor
that can
lead to a uh
uh
uh sorry i'm losing my words that can
lead to a an interaction that is uh that
is optimal
i i brought it in the
physical rosetta stone
as a special case of of low context
asynchronous communication
one can imagine there would be a million
different contexts by which the
analysis of the stone could have been
accelerated such as
a person reading any of them the rules
or
descriptions being enacted or a labeled
image or any number of contexts that we
would use to interpret
and act upon the text that we read
in this setting where we were
historically removed from the creation
then there still was residual context
and it turned out that that was enough
to
interpret
the symbolic
uh
materials
but this is not like the base
communication case
that we then need to see all
communication and all learning and
education of languages and active
inference ontology as being like a
rosetta stone
like the definitions of words are not
codes to crack
they're like inside jokes
or ways of communicating on a sports
team
that have to do with the context of the
setting
and um
asynchronous
modifications in the environment
especially symbolic asynchronous
modifications which are relatively new
potentially existing in their
modern form for several hundreds to
several thousands of years depending on
how we think about it symbolic
asynchronous modification
is
a low context communication
whereas
even the interpretant of asynchronous
symbolic communication
still uses and embodies their context in
the perception so we know that we have
stereophonic communication just because
we're stereophonic
even if we are getting just a morse code
symbol
um
but
it is a
uh non-controversial
here but interestingly it sounds like
elsewhere
that we would want to think about
communication broadly
as being action oriented and embedded
rather than
um kind of like reverse engineered
from the kinds of artifacts that we have
today with quite literally computer
codes
and other kinds of
you know turing computers and so on
okay
i think that you often explain
the ideas that the
the ideas that i'm trying to convey
really better than me
danielle i'm not really fluent in
english so i i thank you for explaining
better than me the the idea that i'm
trying to say
thank you um i appreciate it and
you wrote the paper and so it's
unsurprising it seems
novel
and i couldn't say it in any other way
even when you speak english daniel can
still like speak better than you
communicate more effectively the ideas
that you're trying to convey even when
english is your first language
well
context is non-fungible
so i don't think that there can be
a best or a final communication
it's just like a best or a final species
or state for an ecosystem to be in
and i guess in the last
25 minutes or however
now that our ecosystem has been modified
however it has been
in these conversations and through
reading and
opening up threads
uh how will it
shape our field of affordances
and how will we
stream and play differently dean
so i'm curious from all from all three
of you
as a strategy
if you want to get past monologue what
do you do how many times do you play
playing play so as an example like a
real pertinent one right now
well the way that the live streams about
have been set up have always been
sort of a pre-brief
introduction with the authors or a play
and then a a
played a debrief piece to this and so
the communication is never left as a as
a one-off
exercise
i just read the paper there's a there's
it there is
affordance is set up to interact with
information to be able to receive it
at multiple different time points
because i think in the dot one
you said we could look at it as slices
of time but that's probably not
accurate in terms of of the dynamic
that's in play so
one of the things the active inference
institute also does is
has a
textbook group
now i've not been a part of the text
group book group and i don't know
whether they do it in sets of three as
well to create that kind of
triangulation so that it the interaction
that the communication
doesn't become
monolithic
or monistic
or
here here's here are the words that have
come down now off the mount
accept them and start start carrying
them out even though you don't have a
context right
chiseling them into the stone doesn't
increase their priority at least if you
don't have the context so
what i'm curious about from three of you
is if you want to get past
instructionalism in terms or if you want
to get past transmission
is there a basic
requirement to have multiple
reinterpretations or at least the
opportunity to reinterpret like does it
from a communication standpoint do we
must we have
reflection
and time for that do we have to have
time built in for that or are we are we
then bound
to a transmitted state only
anybody can answer
yes blue first
um
so so not like uh in the way that we
have um reflection like we have a
pre-brief and then the actual brief and
then and then the reflection time in the
live stream series so so not in that way
but but i do think that um
in in effective communication there is
like reflection
as an essential component of that
like communication when you have a
conversation
it
shouldn't be
about just waiting for your turn to talk
right i mean there should be some
reflection of what the other person is
saying
in what you're saying back to them like
hello how are you doing today i want
scrambled eggs like if that was a
conversation when it wouldn't like be it
wouldn't work right like so there has to
be some element of reflecting back what
the other person is saying to you
in in communication that's effective
it's not just this like tower of
disjointed blocks being built
yes remy
yeah i think i think that uh what you
said the blue is is interesting the a
really important element of cooperative
communication is that
when you're talking to somebody when
you're in a dialogue you have to concede
a part of your autonomy you have to
accept to be regulated by the other
person and that's i think
where somebody people who like talk past
each other and don't listen to each
other and interact it happens really
often some friends talk to talk like it
seems like when when they're waiting
they're just waiting when they're
listening they're just waiting to say
what they want to say so
these people don't like don't respect
the kind of pragmatic uh principle uh of
like you you have to to pay attention to
what the other person is saying and to
have a proper to have a correct uh
communicative interaction you have to
concede
the the the
like you have to accept that your field
of affordance is regulated by the person
who's talking to you you have to let
yourself be um
influenced be constrained by the by the
person who's talking to you just because
you you have to listen to it and you
have to uh refrain from like turning
away and go go do something else you
have to um like it's it's really just
accepting considering a part of your
autonomy and that's a another uh idea
from di paolo as a an active approach of
language
where like there's in communicative
interact in inter any cooperative
interaction but in communicative
interaction in particular you have to uh
like here in a bit a part of your field
of affordance to participate in this
interaction and listen because
suppose that what i'm saying is really
boring to you and you just want to go
eat your piece of cake in the in the
fridge like you have to in order to
participate to uh maintain the the the
interaction you have to inhibit this
this afford this solicitation and to uh
to let me regulate your your your field
of affordance and so there's this part
of like i concede i can see something in
order to maintain the interaction and
when there's no no more interest or i'm
not able
to to i don't want to to be regulated
and there's another solicitation outside
the interaction that's more uh
interesting to me but then i will leave
the interaction but
to maintain the interaction you have to
have a
capacity of inhibition executive
executive some form of what would be
called executive control to uh be able
to listen and and take what the person
is saying if you don't have that you're
just going to think about something else
and not let yourself be
take
be constrained by the communicative acts
of the other person
so back to dean's
point about multi-part and multiplayer
communication and engagement
when we only have one communication
then it can feel like a transmission
like the rosetta stone transmitted from
the past we don't get a a dot two or a
dot one on the rosetta stone
structuring learning groups
and other activities and relationships
and cooperative communication
as something unfolding
bumping into each other twice
says something about those particles
that bumping together
just once
doesn't it's almost like
what do they say once is an accident
twice is a coincidence
three times is a party or
something like that
so
especially with three
because one two three
there may be
a
enough of a recurrent engagement and
interweaving
to support reflection development
to de-emphasize any single of those
events
because none of them are even half
of the total series of three
so none of them can even be said to be a
plurality or a majority
if the dot zero one and two were to vote
uh to vote one of them out or something
like that
um
and i think it does point towards
the reality of our continued interaction
with materials
and then
towards
structures that allow us to
engage
naturally remy
i i think that what um
communicating
in there
repetitively with the same people what
it achieves it's
it
obviously it shapes the genetic model it
aligns them in in some ways so
we come to share expectations and
share fields of affordances
so it's it clearly eases uh
communicative interaction because we
don't have to communicate as much when
we there's this trade-off between if you
have a lot of shared context you don't
have
you don't have to communicate as much
and if you don't have a lot of short
context you have to communicate more to
to to
to
yeah have a
useful interaction to have a productive
interaction and so what
i think we we have done is we have like
aligned the arginative models in ways
that helps us understand
each other better than we did at the
beginning
for instance we can refer to things that
we said in the past we can say oh when
you said that
i i so i think that's relevant now and
so we can
make
we can point to relations to things that
that we said earlier so
there's this uh
there's this continual easing of
communication
when you have repetitive communicative
interaction with somebody that's i think
that i think is uh
why we can come to believe that people
we're living with we can reach read each
other's mind without without talking
because there's so much shared context
that something can happen and it can
make us think some something that is
shared without us even saying anything
so there's this this context come to be
really complex and really um
really deep
and so yeah interacting repetitively
obviously eases communication
okay so we can
meet multiple times
do preparation
engagement
and reflection
before during and after
a communication
and structure communication so that
there are multiple
such kind of peaks and troughs
we can
talk about aligning
or
synchronizing in the general synchrony
sense not making identical but rather
coordinating our generative models
through
perception and learning
as you
mentioned it helps us understand each
other better
like a goal of a communication could be
epistemic
let's get to know each other
and it could also have an element of
pragmatic value like let's take
epistemic action to find out if a
collaboration is relevant here
and then we're going to engage in these
pragmatic actions
remy
yeah and i i think that
a lot of
interaction
uh that we share in our like academic
and uh
highly linguistic and advanced societies
really often look like a transmission
interaction so we're saying things that
we're thinking to each other but i think
that these epistemic or communicative um
in terms of transmission
these communicative transmission
interactions
are are the way they are because they
are explicit aims of the interaction in
which we're engaged that is we are
transmitting content now when we're
talking to each other because
that
in a way that that's the goal of of the
interaction
but in in other contexts like
it's because we have communicative
practices that we have developed that we
can have these these goals uh that can
drive an interaction
um if we're at the grocery store if
we're in other contexts we're doing some
something else but when we're in
academic context often the goal of the
interactions is talking about ideas
transmitting some some
some contents transmitting some some
some theories for instance explaining
theories explaining arguments and so
these interactions we we look at them
and we're like oh that's clearly there's
they were transmitting content when
we're talking but the idea is that the
this is really a small subset of the
cases of communicative interaction that
we
engage in in everyday life and we take
these as
paradigmatic uh cases of communicative
interaction when they are really
the the pinnacle of the the the
linguistic civilization we're in in a
really
rarified
[Laughter]
context where like academic discussions
are not what we do
in everyday settings when we talk to
each other and we we do this it's
because it's a an explicit aim of our
interaction now that we do this but in
other cases
in many in most cases when we speak to
each other that's not the the aim the
explicit aim is not to transfer some
information or talk about theories it's
about doing things uh together and now
we're doing something together we're
talking about active influence but
it looks as if it it can be understood
in in terms of content sharing and
content transmission but that's because
it's the goal of our interaction it's
not because it's the nature of
communication
don't i don't know if i'm being clear
yep
dean you had your hand raised
well i just i think
you know i don't want to put my
philosopher's cap on but i will just
briefly i think we use language and
communication to save time it's an
explication strategy
and so i think when we put a 13-week set
of parentheses around a learning
moment or opportunity
we oftentimes get get the card ahead of
the horse we don't we don't see the
pragmatics
because we're busy
transmitting
and what ends up happening is the plan
forward that affordance that
exploitation or optimization or savings
of time
jumps ahead of the prep to participate
in the permeate now
we can say that's a luxury but
is if if we don't respect the fact that
people
maybe don't necessarily learn as well
when they're handed the plan as opposed
to
given an opportunity to build one or
form one themselves through preparation
participation and permeation we could go
away from this live stream and each of
us could literally now design a better
plan
as opposed to
remy came to us with a plan no what remy
came to us with
was a sketch
and then we prepped
participated and permeated that now the
the the sophistication of whatever comes
out of that in terms of a go forward
move for each one of us
is
orders of magnitude greater because
somebody didn't say
oh well i've only got 13 weeks i don't
have the luxury to be able to be
pragmatic about this
so there i'll take my hat off again i
don't mean to sermonize but i think when
we actually
feel what it's like
to let the plan
naturally evolve and and become
a part of the ecology as opposed to
driving the ecology the single source it
changes everything
and over and over again every time we
have one of these three set live streams
it reinforces
what you could do and again you don't
even have to be on
the the
zoo
as long as you give over the amount of
the amount of time to see and sense what
it's like to prep
participate and the
and i think the most important one of
all stick around for the permeate
because that's where the real nuggets
seem to to daniel's
metaphor of icebergs
things float
to the surface
when you give it enough time but i i
understand
it's also a 13-week window and i'm
paying thousands of dollars to
to sit in your class and come on
exploit the daylights out of your
communication
and i just don't know that people don't
realize that they're cutting off their
noses
despite their
their learning
so
interesting a lot
there
permeation letting it
pervade
our generative model or
percolate letting those messages be
passed
letting that ripple or the perturbation
take effect at slower and deeper levels
and
it is really a challenge
when the logistical and transmission
aspects of communication
are scaffolded
and those are like the metadata fields
that have to be filled out the boxes
that have to be checked
and they can feel constraining
yet removing them
is not a positive solution
and so the path of least action for many
learning
scenarios
is to replicate the prior
yep
over the decades a professor
who might teach the same class in the
same way
and there's
pros and cons to that
in fact some of the uh most
enlivened learning communities
have like a vibrancy that transcends
an almost ironically static learning
experience
like we all read this thing so it's not
that that i think the
mode of communication and cooperation
and education that we're exploring here
means that every single experience is
going to be like
some kind of full attention
transformative
depth psychology
i think it would feel more
normal and natural and just like
participating in
a cool ecosystem
that works
with that individual's
situation
what else can we add or where can we go
where is active inference in all of this
where do you see active inference um
not like you know
what are your intentions with my child
but um
where is active inference in your
further research agenda remy
i think it gives the um
the like uh
all-encompassing
framework
and then
yeah the the
the abstractness
of the framework allows us to apply
it to as we said like communicate
communication between cells
and communication between like uh
countries or
groups of individuals for this
multi-scale
property of active inference i think is
really useful in the
in in allowing us to describe
communicative interaction between these
various kinds of
of
free energy minimizing uh
uh
yeah agents
um
i saw that there's this did that
that's useful i think that the
yeah the the the learning mechanisms
that are uh
that are at work in active influence are
really useful also
to
explain how communicative interaction is
conducted and how repeated communicative
interaction can lead to a form of
synchronizing of the generative model as
has been explored by vasil in a paper
and in 2020 i think so that i think
that's uh that's really useful uh
there's a lot of a lot of things that uh
that i think we can take from the active
inference framework and
and and yeah
the the the idea that all actual i think
the fundamental intuition is that all
all action is
free energy minimization
that's trivial that that's uh
but
i think there's a pragmatist uh insight
in in active influence that we can use
to um to
uh
to
support
the uh
the pragmatist view of communication
yeah yeah that everything that an
organism does it does it to minimize the
free energy and active influence is no
different
and coming a communicative active
influence as a form of active influence
also aims to minimize the free energy of
an organism and so when an organism
tries it finds itself in in a situation
where it's
there's a lot of free energy there's a
lot of error prediction it will try to
engage it in its environment intervene
it's an environment in order to
bring itself back in in
viable in its viable states and so all
these ideas and when we apply them to
communication i think they lead
not necessarily by implication but i
think they there's a
path to these ideas through the the
to the the pragmatic view of
communication the idea that that
communication is another form of is just
a mechanism of regulation
of organisms in order to minimize their
free energy i think there's this kind of
basic
uh biological um
understanding of the the behavior of
organism i think it leads us more toward
the pragmatist viewer community of
communication
rather than uh toward the the the more
informational or transmission view that
is
that is more
at home in our like really
highly uh advanced and complex
linguistic interaction and i think that
this like basic biological framework
uh is is a good place to start to
understand uh communication in the
pragmatist view
very nice
answer
i'll i'll read a comment from steven and
then we can
give a thought on it as well as provide
some closing thoughts
so stephen wrote
explicit aims of interaction are
important and can be invisible thus
communication appears to be based on
transmission should we identify the
context through the affordances or via
naming the water like the water we swim
in
that is
is the context and the explicit aims
apparent via the affordances
or is there a special sauce that flavors
the cultural waters in which we are
swimming
yes dean special sausage
on that i think
what maybe it did build on what remy
just said i think
perhaps active inference
opens up that space
to the to the idea of a special sauce it
doesn't guarantee that there will be one
and it certainly doesn't um promise
but what it does do is it says what are
the possibilities
within this not just
what are we collapsing down to i mean
i'm throughout this series i've been
talking a lot about well we can't leave
the absolutes the things that we've
experienced out of this equation but i
think what the what i think the active
inference affords is that
those relativities those in those those
entailments and those entanglements
always to be determined can be moved
towards
and and may be accepted
with with more abundance
if we use active influence but that's
just my optimistic take on it
do you have any other closing words
before we hear some final thoughts from
the others
excellent okay
blue
or remy with some
final thoughts how is this
how will it permeate with you
okay so i'll go ahead so yeah
i i was really happy to have the chance
to talk uh about the paper with you i
think that one of the most important
things that i'll take home uh
is that now i have a really uh salient
solicitation to go see the plant robot
uh
in action so like uh at the second that
i close the zoom meeting i'm going to go
see that that's really something that i
i'm taking from the this this discussion
uh but yeah no it was really interesting
to see different perspectives different
background
uh uh
what what
these different different backgrounds
can bring
to a discussion
that is
i think that was really enlightening for
me and i was really happy to
to be there
i'll just say thanks for coming remy we
really enjoyed this discussion and for
me i think what will permeate is like
the
you know everything i think about now i
just like think about how can i model
this in terms of active inference
and i feel like this paper will um you
know influence maybe the way that i
think about
communication which is a big part of
modeling active inference period
especially like in a multi-agent
dynamical system so i think i i will
probably leverage this ecological
approach in the way that i think about
it going forward so i appreciate the
opportunity to learn about it
awesome
my
closing thought what i'm left with here
is
active inference
as about affordances
it is about the the content of the model
is about affordances and active
inference is an affordance
it allows us to
realize epistemic and pragmatic value
today and in the future
and in that way
we can
see it as gripper and gripped
just like we could talk about the hand
as gripper engripped whether it's
holding hands or grabbing an object
and especially in this dot too
some very
nice points added
on language as gripper and gripped
and contextualizing this kind of
breakaway verbal community
of
research
and scholarly education in academia and
recognizing that breakaway
community and skill
as something that's crystallizing out of
a much more inclusive and pragmatically
oriented niche
and i think that will be
a win-win framing
because it will
help ground what can be abstract and
lofty discussions
and also
elevate and
bring what
bring attention
and support to some
areas and types of communication
that are
absolutely natural in the field of
affordance view and the ecological view
but are not always respected so highly
under like a symbolic transmission view
and
the closing image for me is making the
sauce underwater
i'm just imagining it's like i don't
know spongebob squarepants or someone's
trying to cook and make the sauce but
we're adding things and it's more just
like happening in this diffuse of space
and in a way all kitchens are in fluids
that's why we can smell
what we're cooking but it's different
enough
that the sauce stays in the pan and i
think the social inaction of active
inference is when
the sauce
is spilling out of the pan
all right
remy you're always welcome back so
hopefully
you'll share some developments in this
line good luck with the rest of your
work
thanks thank you
all right farewell
bye
you